Unbelievable. It was brilliant!
I loved it. It was...
It's really good.
All right, OK, let's get this over with.
Come on then, Mr F1 Fan, I'm braced
and ready for your comments. Go.
I agree with you. Eh?
I do agree with you.
The Americans are very bad at some
things, they can't say aluminium,
and they can't win a
war without our help,
but they are very good
at making dreary sports
very exciting to watch.
Let's just take, for an
example, rounders. Right?
That's played by small
children here, over there,
it's Babe Ruth, and a religion.
Then you've got netball which
here is schoolgirls standing,
so you can only move one foot, and
there's four parents watching,
and over there it's, what is it?
Harlem Globetrotters.
They are quite easily amused.
Unbelievably easily
amused, and that's why
they're able to make
NASCAR exciting.
It's just some good ol' boys going
round in a circle. And they go,
"Oh, hell, I'll go pay to watch that."
250,000 people turn up to watch it.
Because it is a good sport.
I mean Hammond you would say that,
because you're an American.
Wait a minute, I'm not.
You've got a Stetson, cowboy boots,
chaps, a Harley-Davidson, a Mustang,
you like to get a beer and you
put cheese on everything.
I don't! I'm not American.
You have made a living out
of being... an American.
Your Saturday night programme is
a fat man falling off some foam rubber.
"Oh, right, hey, we'll watch that!"
Then they turn up in their millions.
APPLAUSE
JAMES HUMS STAR SPANGLED BANNER
I'm not an American.
Look, Hammond, I wish the
Americans... ran a decent sport,
if they got Formula 1, it would be
fantastic, because they would say,
"Let's have sprinklers
coming on at random points
"during the race," and
that would be fantastic.
There would be no more
stewards' enquiries,
and there will be no more of this,
"You've got a ten second drive-by
penalty," which ruins the race.
They would say, "Hamilton and
Masa... you don't get on,
after the race, in your boxes,
"on the winner's podium, slug it out."
Yeah. I'd watch that,
would you watch that?
I'd watch that. It would be brilliant.
I would watch that.
Anyway, we must do the news.
We are starting with the
Institute of Advanced Motorists,
you know the ones.
Oh, yeah, them.
They are the ones who...
They say that you mustn't cross
hands on the steering wheel.
You've got to shuffle it, like that.
Never drive one-handed,
they don't like that.
They prefer that.
Is anyone here in The Institute
of Advanced Motorists?
Like you are going to confess it now.
You are! So you are in the Institute?
So, you do this?
Did you drive down...
here today like this?
You're a passenger?
Oh, you can knock yourself out, then.
The Institute of Advanced Motorists...
has launched a new thing called,
Drive And Survive.
What, rather than Drive And Die?
That would never work.
Drive And Survive, OK?
The idea is, what they've got is,
every week they're
offering motoring tips.
Yes, so this week it's parking.
I'll give you a couple of examples
they've come up with, right?
"Park on the left-hand side
of the road if possible,
"and always at night."
Eh? What happens if you
arrive at lunch time?
I parked here this morning.
You didn't! I did. You idiot!
Park always at night.
Another one, right?
This is one I really can't get.
"When parking, open your
window in car parks,
"and turn off your stereo.
You can often hear something,
"before you can see it."
What, a lamppost? Lampposts actually
make a very soft cooing sound.
Do they?
I once heard a squelching
sound, and then a pop,
but that was the neighbour's cat!
Can we move on? Yes.
I have some news, there is a new
Dodge Viper being announced,
and apparently it's going to employ
Fiat technology on it, which is...
They mean is there's a new one,
and it won't work properly.
They haven't said that.
I suspect that Dodge
are a little worried
about the styling they have chosen,
because this is the
photograph they have sent.
Doesn't tell you much, does it?
Doesn't tell you a lot. Maybe it's shy?
Hey, now, you know sometimes
you meet someone who has
a growth on their face, and it's
actually bigger than their face?
Have you ever seen that?
No, I mean... one of those
really ugly things.
No, this is just a face, I'm talking
about a growth. That's your face?
I bring this up, because
there's a company in Japan
whose obviously used this growth thing
as an inspiration for their
new Prius campervan.
Here it is. Oh, God!
It's the elephant car. It is.
SLURS SPEECH: I'm so
pleased to meet you.
I hope nobody knocks my trailer over.
It's a monster.
You've got a double bed in the
and another one in that growth.
That is not a car that you
could talk to at a party,
unless you are looking
at something else.
I've got news from Renault,
they've got a new car, I've
got a picture of it here,
it's called the Influenza. Is it?
It isn't called the Influenza.
Well, it's something a bit like that.
It's electric, as you can, because
there it is plugged in, recharging.
I was wondering, when in the future,
when we're all driving electric cars,
the cities are full of
these charging points,
won't ten-year-old boys go
around unplugging cars?
That's what we would have
done when I was ten.
Do you have to be ten, why wouldn't...
you do that aged, I don't know, 52?
Well, quite.
You would know though... wouldn't you?
If you saw somebody parked, you
would just go... You would.
I wouldn't. Why would you do that?
Remember the early Fiat Panda, the
boxy one that Giugiaro designed,
whenever I walk past one of
those with a group of friends,
we always picked it up
and turned it around.
You could just...
I was going that way,
how is that happened?
In the same way as it's always great fun
to lock someone else's bicycle
up with your bicycle lock.
You're just a yobbo!
Come on, Hammond, you
must have done that?
Or throw a brick through their
window, or set fire to their shop.
If you go to Halfords, you buy a whole
load of really cheap bicycle locks.
The combination ones... Then go along
the street, locking people's bikes up.
Why would you do that?
Because it's funny!
No, it is, because you do it,
and I did this with Robert
Cook on York station, in 1978,
if it was your bicycle,
you'll know it was us.
You lock it, hide behind some bins,
Wait for them to come back.
They take their lock off,
"Yes, my bicycle's good,"
and they go off and go,
"I didn't put that on there.
"People are watching, getting ideas...
Don't do this, ten-year-olds and
52-year-olds, we're not condoning this.
52-year-old children.
Or indeed unplugging
peoples' electric cars,
because when they come back and find
the range says two, it's not funny.
It is funny.
We're not saying you should do that.
No, you shouldn't.
Were just saying you can do that.
Last week we revealed that the
police were claiming that
driving under the influence
of a cold remedy
is the same as driving under
the influence of cocaine.
Now, I drove down here,
because I got a cold that
I haven't... mentioned,
I drove down here this morning
having taken some Day Nurse,
and I arrived without incident.
Did it make you very boring, and
overly confident at parties?
No, I'm always that, I was that anyway.
So, I'm just letting you know that Day
Nurse and driving are OK. I made it.
Yeah, on that subject actually
last week, you agreed,
in fact you challenged James
to do a lap of a track,
you would be sewing on a button
at the same time as driving,
he would be in a sleeping bag.
Yes, and you would be
giving yourself pleasure.
Those are the rules, so are we going...
to have our race? We did promise.
I've forgotten my sleeping bag, sir,
I've been practising all week.
I promise we will do our sleeping
bag, sewing a button on,
and Hammond race before
the end of the series.
Moving on, Mercedes SLS,
James and Richard will tell you
that it's too big and too stupid.
It is. It is. No, it isn't.
It is a SUPERB car, and
as far as I'm concerned,
there is only one thing wrong with it...
its doors.
That two things!
Well, it is, it's too doors.
Thank you, Hammond.