blog.naver.com/incusx
S18E02 - 12.02.05
Estoque - blog.naver.com
오늘밤, 전 미끄러집니다.
리처드는 타이어를 몇개 훔치고요
제임스는 얼굴을 까입니다.
안녕하세요. 감사합니다. 모두들 감사합니다.
자,
시작부터 이거 하나 만큼은 확실히 해두고 가도록 합시다.
포뮬러1은 나스카보다 훨씬 낫습니다.
진짜 그래요.
이것들을 두가지 악기에 비유하자면,
F1은 스트라디바리우스 바이올린이고
나스카는 나무 숟가락으로 냄비를 두드리는것과 같죠.
바로 문명화된 우리 사회에서 모두가 동의하는 바입니다.
음, 제가 동의를 했다고 하는 "우리"는 말이죠,
"우리"중에서 리처드 J. 치즈버거 해먼드 3세를 제외한 겁니다.
나스카의 우월성을 믿는 사람은 저뿐만이 아니라고 생각합니다.
이것은 현재 미국에서 가장 많은 관람객을 유치하는 경기입니다.
그리고 이것이 팬들의 관심을 끌 수 있었던 이유는 많았습니다.
첫 번째는 이것의 근원입니다.
포뮬러1과는 다르게 나스카는 부유한 양아치와 귀족들의 여가시간용이 아니라,
매우 보잘것없고 노동자 계급적인 기원을 가지고 있습니다.
나스카의 역사는 1940년부터 시작됩니다.
밀주 운반가들, 그러니까 버릇없는 촌놈들이 불법으로 제조한 술을
국경선을 따라 밀수하며 경찰을 따돌리기 위해서
그들의 차를 개조하는게 시초였습니다.
무언가가 다른 것을 끌어당기는 것은 여러분이 눈치체지도 못하게 일어나는데요,
그들은 저녁시간에 비공식적인 레이스 모임을 가지곤 했는데,
흙이 가득한 벌판이 즉석에서 레이스 트랙이 되곤 했습니다.
밀주 운반가들이 선호하는 차는 바로 이런 유형의 차입니다.
바로 훌륭하게 생긴 1941년산 포드 비즈니스 쿠페인데
왜냐면 지나가는 경찰관의 의심을 사지 않았으니까요.
분명히 이런 차를 타고 다니는 사람은 비즈니스를 하러 가는 사람일 것이라고 생각했겠지요.
왜 경찰들이 그런 사람을 귀찮게 하겠어요?
차 아래에는 고성능으로 개조된 엔진, 강화한 서스펜션과
내부에는 불법 제조술을 운반하기위한 비밀 수납함이 있습니다.
이차는 실제로 밀주 운반가들이 썼던 차입니다.
국경지대를 따라서 밀주를 싣고 경찰을 따돌리며 다닌 후
나스카에 참가하러 가게 된거죠. 이건 레알 이에요!
몇 십 년이 지난 후 경기의 규모는 커졌습니다.
'찰나의 실수가 낳은 고장은 여파가 엄청날 것입니다.'
하지만 법밖에 존재하는 것을 선호하는 성향은 아직도 남아있습니다.
1950년도 초를 예로 들자면, 롤케이지는 나스카 레이싱에서 의무사항이었습니다.
하지만 드라이버들은 하나같이
‘에이 무슨.... 차무게도 약간 늘어나고 롤케이지를 다는 건 여자나 하는 짓이야’ 라고 하며,
그들은 롤케이지랑 비슷하게 생긴 물건들을.... 대신 달았습니다.
예를 들어 잘린 나무토막 같은 걸로 말이죠.
제가 이 스포츠를 좋아하는 또 하나의 이유는,
그것의 반항아 적인 기질을 제외 하고 말씀드리자면,
우주비행선급의 기술이 F1에서는 목격하실 수 있지만,
나스카 머신들은 매력적으로 간단합니다.
저는 텍사스 스피드웨이의 경기 일에 이것에 관한 설명을 들을 수 있었습니다.
이차가 800마력을 낸다고요?
지미 존슨
나스카 5회 챔피언
거의 900가까이 되죠.
900마력이라..
900마력이에요.
어떤 전자제어장치도 안 달려있죠? 단지....
그렇습니다. 말 그대로 카뷰레터 엔진이죠.
음, 나스카는 드라이버가 되도록이면 트랙의 정보를 알지 못하게 합니다.
그래서 저는 어떤 데이터도 모르는 체로 이차에서 느끼는 감각을 모두 다 설명해야 하죠.
예를 들자면 서스펜션의 변화나, 쇼크업쇼버의 변화, 형상이라던지...
당신이요?
네,
그러면 어떤 것도 노트북 컴퓨터로 다운로드 받지 않겠네요?
그렇습니다, 저희는 심지어 자동차에 연료가 떨어졌다는걸 알려주는 연료 센서조차 없습니다.
그리고 이 작은 것들, 이게 바로...
이게 바로 자동차가 스핀을 할 때 항력을 만들어 내구요 또 오른쪽 창에 있는것은...
이게 차가 뒤집히지 않게 한다는 건 말도 안되는 소리에요!
풍동터널에서 시험해본결과 정말 그렇다네요.
그러니까, 이게 정말 도움이 되는 이유는....
이게 열리면,
차량 위쪽에 저기압이 형성되구요
이게 열리면서 차가 다시 아래쪽으로 내려가는것을 돕습니다.
그러니까 저게 스핀할때 뒤집히는걸 방지 해준다는 거네요.
네, 여기에도 있어요.
음, 저건 마치 랜드로버의 앞에 달린 환풍구 같군요.
그렇게 초 신기술은 아니네요.
여러분이 F1팬에 나스카를 힐난하는 사람이라면,
제 생각에는 여러분이 할 말을 정확하게 알고 있습니다.... 만약 여기 계신다면요.
'이건, 음, 쉬워 보이는데.'
'그냥 액셀 밟고 왼쪽으로 돌면 되는거 아닌가'
그리고 정말 그래요. 진짜로요.
반면에 포물러1은 코너들 같은 건 좀 외워둬야 하죠.
어려워요.
그래서 이 드라이버들이 연간 약 255억을 받는건
F1드라이버들보다 쉽게 돈을 버는 셈일까요?
글쎄요, 둘 다 해본사람한테 물어보도록 합시다.
차는 모는 것 말이에요? 저는 F1과는 전혀 다르다는걸 말씀드리고 싶네요.
주앙 파블로 몬토야
전직 F1, CART 드라이버, 현재는 나스카 출전
이차들이 더 예측 불허입니다.
끝도 없이 미끄러지며, 브레이크조차 제대로 작동을 안 해요.
제 말은, 브레이크가 안 듣는다는 것의 말뜻은요
바로 차가 너무 무겁고, 브레이크가 너무 작아서 그래요
진심으로, 오벌 트랙이 제 생각에 더 어려운 것 같습니다.
제프 고든
나스카 4회 챔피언
왜냐면, 코너가 저 멀리서 시작 되고
저 멀리 반대쪽에서 끝나게 되니까요.
그리고 차가 움직인다면서요?
자동차는 항상 움직입니다. 가만히 있질 않아요.
그리고 다른 차들이 함께 달릴 때는 사이에서 난기류가 발생합니다.
만약 그들이 당신의 바깥쪽에 있으면 잡아당길 것이고,
앞쪽에 있다면 접지력이 생기질 않죠.
이런 게 바로 사람들의 흥미를 엄청나게 끄는 요소인 것 같습니다.
왜냐면 평균 시속 304킬로미터 이상으로 달리면서,
많은 차량들이 서로 간에 2.5센티미터 정도 밖에 안 떨어져있거든요
그리고 이 코너를 3대에서 4대가 함께 돌죠.
실버스톤에 가게 되면 당신은 그... 스탠드에서 서서 '위융' 하고 나면
다시 1분 30초를 기다려야 하잖아요
만약에 순위가 바뀌는 게 보고 싶으면요.
그렇죠.
하지만 대부분 그런 일은 잘 안 일어 나죠.
걔내들은 올해의 추월 많이 한 선수 같은 상도 주잖아요.
왜냐면 당신이 엿 같은 한해동안 겨우 3명 추월했으니까요.
그래서, 딱 붙이서 달리며 몰기 힘든 차량이 있기에
그 말은, 보너스로 이런걸 많이 볼 수 있다는거죠.
말하자면, 접촉이 많은 스포츠에요.
엄청나게 많은 접촉은 불만감에서 나온 것이거나,
다른 놈보고 길을 비키게 만들려고 하는 것이죠.
단지 추월하려고 들이 받을 필요는 없잖아요!
범퍼는 그럴 때 쓰라고 만든 거잖아요!
그리고 이런 것들이 한대 모이면,
나스카 운전자들은... 권고사항에 대해서는 신경을 안 쓰게 됩니다.
어떻게 싸우는지 한번 볼까요? 하빅이 몬토야에게 정말 화가 많이 났군요.
싸움이 일어날까요?
그가 차 속도를 늦추고 있습니다. 그리고 약간의 대화를 하려는 거 같네요.
이것은 역시나 하버드 교수진이라고 오인할일이 전혀 없는 하드코어 팬들에게는 보너스가 됩니다.
주말 레이스 날에는 그들이 주된 식단은 맥주와
붉은 고기 입니다.
샐러드 먹는걸 보신적은 없나요?
샐러드요?
그리고 F1팬보다 더 많은 접근성을 가지고 있습니다.
저게 실제 팬들이 차를 모는거라구요?!
저건 펜들이 줄을 서서 돈을 내고 전문가,
그러니까 드라이버와 함께 트랙을 한 바퀴 도는거랍니다.
F1에서 만약 저런 일을 할 수 있다고 하면 그게 상상이나 가나요?
저런걸 F1에서 할 수 있다면 전 내일 당장 보러갑니다.
저렇게 차가 한 무더기로 달리면, 심지어 자기 차도 아니잖아요. 만약 한대가....
저것보세요, 운전자는 저나 여러분 같은 관중이에요.
저는 오벌을 돌 수 있는 똑같은 기회를 가질 거라는 예상은 하지 않고 있었는데,
바로 그때 저는 드라이버 브리핑 시간에 참여하라는 말을 들었습니다.
저는 그 곳에서 깜짝 출연을 하려 했죠.
미 공군에서 오신 4성 장군 마크 A. 웰스 3세와 그의 아내인 베티 웰시 입니다.
톱기어 영국에서 오신 오늘의 영광스런 페이스카 드라이버,
영국 버밍엄 출신 리처드 해먼드 입니다.
경기를 시작할때가 되었습니다.
국가가 끝나고,
제트 팩을 입은 사람이 착륙한 뒤....
그리고 B-52 폭격기가 위로 날아갔습니다.
제가 43대의 차들을 그리드로 안내해서 포메이션 랩을 할 때가 되었습니다.
제 뒤에 수백만대가 따라오는 기분인데요.
리처드 해먼드, 시동꺼먹지마, 망치지 말라고.
제 뒤에는 39000마력이 달리고 싶어서 안달하고 있습니다.
전 무서워서 백미러를 볼 수가 없습니다. 마치 호랑이떼에게 공격당하는 기분이에요.
오, 제발 쫌!
진입로 개방 완료
출발!
저희가 시작한거에요! 저희가요.
그리고 제게 주어진 특별한 대우는 여기서 그치지 않았습니다.
왜냐면 실제 레이스 시간동안 팀 중의 하나를 돕기로 했거든요.
그리고 제게 아주 중요한 임무를 맡겼습니다.
그래요, 저도 팀원이에요, 지나갑니다. 아 좋다.
전 나스카 레이스의 한 가지 문제점은 500바퀴가 넘는 것 이라는걸 알고 있습니다.
그래서 이 시점에 저희가 할 수 있는 일은...
우리는 몽타주가 필요해 (몽타주)
몽타주를 찍자 (몽타주)
여러 가지 많은 일들을 한 번에 보여주고
우리들에게 어떻게 돌아가는질 알려주지
그게 바로 몽타주라는거야 (몽타주)
오, 우리는 몽타주를 원해 (몽타주)
언제나 몽타주에는 페이드아웃이 있지
만약 네가 이걸 페이드아웃 시킨다면...
꼼수가 잘 먹힌 거 같네요, 그리고 530바퀴가 지난 후에 우리는 우승자를 알게 되었습니다.
3시간하고 20분이 지나자 경기가 쏜살같이 끝났습니다.
저기에 오늘의 우승자가 이제 하늘에 6연발 권총을 쏘고,
새 스테트슨을 쓴 그는 기분이 좋아 보입니다.
흔히 카우보이 모자라고 불리는 형태의 모자
그리고 모든 서커스 단원은 다음 장소로 이동을 하고 이걸 또 합니다.
그리고 많은 논쟁이 있었고 말하자면 이게 증명하고 있는데요,
F1은 너무 심각해보이니까, 여기서 많은 것을 배워갈 수 있을겁니다.
다음날 아침 텅빈 텍사스 스피드 웨이에는 저를 위한 마지막 특별 대우가 있었습니다.
바로 이거죠. 나스카의 전설인 카일 페티에게 배우는 운전 연습 입니다.
이건 제가 몰아 봤던 어떤 차들과는 완전 다른 느낌이네요
제 말은, 이놈이 전혀 직진을 하려 하지 않네요, 정말 그래요.
차가 왼쪽으로만 가려고 하지, 절대로 직진 하려고 하진 않습니다.
잔디를 밟아요, 잔디를 밟고 가야해요,
마치 목초지를 배듯이 잔디를 밟아야 합니다. 더 세게요.
좋아요, 죽 따라가세요.
너무 무서워요!
좀 더 밟아요, 좀 더, 더, 더.
오, 맙소사!
벽에서 딱 붙여서 차를 몰아가세요.
지금 벽옆으로 달리고 있잖아요!
마침내, 카일은 제가 스스로 달릴 수 있게 해주었습니다.
접지력이 살아날 때까지 내버려 두고, 너무 몰아붙이지 말아야 합니다.
이건 단지 크기만 한 원형트랙이 아닙니다. 입체적인 3차원이에요.
그리고 저는 거대하고 소리치는 용안에 타서 레슬링을 하며 달리고 있습니다.
이 코너를 지금 빠져나가서.... 직선주로로 갑니다.
자 갑니다. 가속페달을 밟고요!
이럴 수가!
전 지금 다시 폭팔속에 있습니다!
도대체 접지력은 언제 생기는 거야?
제 폐의 거의 전부가 한쪽으로 쏠려 있어요, 이건 일반적인 상황이 아니죠.
그리고, 설상가상으로...
오, 안 돼, 저건 백미러에서 보고 싶은 게 아니에요.
이건 너무 실제 상황 같잖아요.
저런 건 필요 없어요!
아아앍!
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
Unbelievable. It was brilliant!
I loved it. It was...
It's really good.
All right, OK, let's get this over with.
Come on then, Mr F1 Fan, I'm braced
and ready for your comments. Go.
I agree with you. Eh?
I do agree with you.
The Americans are very bad at some
things, they can't say aluminium,
and they can't win a
war without our help,
but they are very good
at making dreary sports
very exciting to watch.
Let's just take, for an
example, rounders. Right?
That's played by small
children here, over there,
it's Babe Ruth, and a religion.
Then you've got netball which
here is schoolgirls standing,
so you can only move one foot, and
there's four parents watching,
and over there it's, what is it?
Harlem Globetrotters.
They are quite easily amused.
Unbelievably easily
amused, and that's why
they're able to make
NASCAR exciting.
It's just some good ol' boys going
round in a circle. And they go,
"Oh, hell, I'll go pay to watch that."
250,000 people turn up to watch it.
Because it is a good sport.
I mean Hammond you would say that,
because you're an American.
Wait a minute, I'm not.
You've got a Stetson, cowboy boots,
chaps, a Harley-Davidson, a Mustang,
you like to get a beer and you
put cheese on everything.
I don't! I'm not American.
You have made a living out
of being... an American.
Your Saturday night programme is
a fat man falling off some foam rubber.
"Oh, right, hey, we'll watch that!"
Then they turn up in their millions.
APPLAUSE
JAMES HUMS STAR SPANGLED BANNER
I'm not an American.
Look, Hammond, I wish the
Americans... ran a decent sport,
if they got Formula 1, it would be
fantastic, because they would say,
"Let's have sprinklers
coming on at random points
"during the race," and
that would be fantastic.
There would be no more
stewards' enquiries,
and there will be no more of this,
"You've got a ten second drive-by
penalty," which ruins the race.
They would say, "Hamilton and
Masa... you don't get on,
after the race, in your boxes,
"on the winner's podium, slug it out."
Yeah. I'd watch that,
would you watch that?
I'd watch that. It would be brilliant.
I would watch that.
Anyway, we must do the news.
We are starting with the
Institute of Advanced Motorists,
you know the ones.
Oh, yeah, them.
They are the ones who...
They say that you mustn't cross
hands on the steering wheel.
You've got to shuffle it, like that.
Never drive one-handed,
they don't like that.
They prefer that.
Is anyone here in The Institute
of Advanced Motorists?
Like you are going to confess it now.
You are! So you are in the Institute?
So, you do this?
Did you drive down...
here today like this?
You're a passenger?
Oh, you can knock yourself out, then.
The Institute of Advanced Motorists...
has launched a new thing called,
Drive And Survive.
What, rather than Drive And Die?
That would never work.
Drive And Survive, OK?
The idea is, what they've got is,
every week they're
offering motoring tips.
Yes, so this week it's parking.
I'll give you a couple of examples
they've come up with, right?
"Park on the left-hand side
of the road if possible,
"and always at night."
Eh? What happens if you
arrive at lunch time?
I parked here this morning.
You didn't! I did. You idiot!
Park always at night.
Another one, right?
This is one I really can't get.
"When parking, open your
window in car parks,
"and turn off your stereo.
You can often hear something,
"before you can see it."
What, a lamppost? Lampposts actually
make a very soft cooing sound.
Do they?
I once heard a squelching
sound, and then a pop,
but that was the neighbour's cat!
Can we move on? Yes.
I have some news, there is a new
Dodge Viper being announced,
and apparently it's going to employ
Fiat technology on it, which is...
They mean is there's a new one,
and it won't work properly.
They haven't said that.
I suspect that Dodge
are a little worried
about the styling they have chosen,
because this is the
photograph they have sent.
Doesn't tell you much, does it?
Doesn't tell you a lot. Maybe it's shy?
Hey, now, you know sometimes
you meet someone who has
a growth on their face, and it's
actually bigger than their face?
Have you ever seen that?
No, I mean... one of those
really ugly things.
No, this is just a face, I'm talking
about a growth. That's your face?
I bring this up, because
there's a company in Japan
whose obviously used this growth thing
as an inspiration for their
new Prius campervan.
Here it is. Oh, God!
It's the elephant car. It is.
SLURS SPEECH: I'm so
pleased to meet you.
I hope nobody knocks my trailer over.
It's a monster.
You've got a double bed in the
and another one in that growth.
That is not a car that you
could talk to at a party,
unless you are looking
at something else.
I've got news from Renault,
they've got a new car, I've
got a picture of it here,
it's called the Influenza. Is it?
It isn't called the Influenza.
Well, it's something a bit like that.
It's electric, as you can, because
there it is plugged in, recharging.
I was wondering, when in the future,
when we're all driving electric cars,
the cities are full of
these charging points,
won't ten-year-old boys go
around unplugging cars?
That's what we would have
done when I was ten.
Do you have to be ten, why wouldn't...
you do that aged, I don't know, 52?
Well, quite.
You would know though... wouldn't you?
If you saw somebody parked, you
would just go... You would.
I wouldn't. Why would you do that?
Remember the early Fiat Panda, the
boxy one that Giugiaro designed,
whenever I walk past one of
those with a group of friends,
we always picked it up
and turned it around.
You could just...
I was going that way,
how is that happened?
In the same way as it's always great fun
to lock someone else's bicycle
up with your bicycle lock.
You're just a yobbo!
Come on, Hammond, you
must have done that?
Or throw a brick through their
window, or set fire to their shop.
If you go to Halfords, you buy a whole
load of really cheap bicycle locks.
The combination ones... Then go along
the street, locking people's bikes up.
Why would you do that?
Because it's funny!
No, it is, because you do it,
and I did this with Robert
Cook on York station, in 1978,
if it was your bicycle,
you'll know it was us.
You lock it, hide behind some bins,
Wait for them to come back.
They take their lock off,
"Yes, my bicycle's good,"
and they go off and go,
"I didn't put that on there.
"People are watching, getting ideas...
Don't do this, ten-year-olds and
52-year-olds, we're not condoning this.
52-year-old children.
Or indeed unplugging
peoples' electric cars,
because when they come back and find
the range says two, it's not funny.
It is funny.
We're not saying you should do that.
No, you shouldn't.
Were just saying you can do that.
Last week we revealed that the
police were claiming that
driving under the influence
of a cold remedy
is the same as driving under
the influence of cocaine.
Now, I drove down here,
because I got a cold that
I haven't... mentioned,
I drove down here this morning
having taken some Day Nurse,
and I arrived without incident.
Did it make you very boring, and
overly confident at parties?
No, I'm always that, I was that anyway.
So, I'm just letting you know that Day
Nurse and driving are OK. I made it.
Yeah, on that subject actually
last week, you agreed,
in fact you challenged James
to do a lap of a track,
you would be sewing on a button
at the same time as driving,
he would be in a sleeping bag.
Yes, and you would be
giving yourself pleasure.
Those are the rules, so are we going...
to have our race? We did promise.
I've forgotten my sleeping bag, sir,
I've been practising all week.
I promise we will do our sleeping
bag, sewing a button on,
and Hammond race before
the end of the series.
Moving on, Mercedes SLS,
James and Richard will tell you
that it's too big and too stupid.
It is. It is. No, it isn't.
It is a SUPERB car, and
as far as I'm concerned,
there is only one thing wrong with it...
its doors.
That two things!
Well, it is, it's too doors.
Thank you, Hammond.
You might imagine, as you drive along
that people will think the
gullwing doors hark back
to the magnificent 300 SL from 1954,
but I suspect they won't
think anything of the sort.
What they will think, as you
pull up and get out is,
"What a massive show off,"
and there's another problem
with gullwing doors as well
because if you roll the car,
how do you open them to get out?
You're trapped in there, soaked
in petrol, burning, screaming.
Now, to prevent that from happening,
Mercedes has fitted the hinges
with explosive bolts that
are designed to fire
if the car goes upside down.
So, these doors then,
what they are are heavy,
unnecessary, embarrassing bombs.
Now however there is a solution.
The SLS Roadster, a car which
offers all of the coupe's thrills,
without leaving you purple-faced
with embarrassment,
every time you get out of it.
That is my idea of the perfect car.
But it is quite difficult
to explain why.
First of all, it costs as near as
makes no difference, £200,000.
Which means it's in the same sort
of price bracket as a Rolls-Royce.
And with a Rolls-Royce you get more...
car.
Of course, with this you get
the magnificent jackhammer
50 cal, AMG soundtrack.
ENGINE REVS
But if that's all you want, why
not buy a much cheaper C-Class?
This four-door saloon makes
exactly... the same sort of racket.
ENGINE REVS
For around a quarter of the price.
Of course, you may say, "A-ha, I
like being exposed to the elements."
I understand that, but I'll
let you into a little secret,
once you're doing 70 miles
an hour in a convertible,
all you really notice is the
wind rushing through your hair,
nothing about the car at all, the
wind is an all-consuming thing.
So, 70 miles an hour
feels exactly the same
whether you're in this,
or this, or this.
Let me put it this way, when
you're... being attacked by a lion,
it doesn't really matter whether
you're in a bungalow or a mansion.
Being attacked by a
lion is the main thing.
Of course, at this point you may say,
"Yes, but I want a big V8
rear drive sports car."
So, what's wrong with this?
The big V8 rear drive Jaguar XKR.
It's very similar to the
Mercedes, except that to my eye,
it looks even better, and is
less than half the price.
Of course, you may think
the SLS is more technical,
more spectacular, and
that's true, it is.
The engine is a masterpiece.
The seven speed, double clutch gearbox
is mounted at the back for
better weight distribution.
It's light. The prop shaft
is made from carbon fibre
and only weighs four kilograms.
And all the little changes they've made
to the suspension on the
convertible are so successful
they're applying them
to the coupe as well.
However don't be fooled
into thinking this is
some kind of track-munching
driver's car...
TYRES SQUEAL
because, it isn't. Argh!
Woah! God, strewth.
It doesn't grip, steer, stop,
or turn anything like
as well as a Ferrari.
Or an Aston Martin DBS, or even a BMW.
HE LAUGHS
BMW M3.
You know what this is like,
an old American muscle car.
A Dodge Charger with a
three-pointed star on the nose.
You could almost call it crude.
So, there are many, many reasons
why you would not buy an SLS,
but there's one why you would,
because it is fantastic.
Cars these days are
also safe, and refined,
and they're all built in
wheat-free multi-ethnic factories,
with one eye on Johnny polar
bear, but this just isn't.
It's just a gigantic,
two-fingered noisy salute
to the whole concept of
sustainable eco-ism.
It's as in tune with the times
as a blaze at an oil refinery,
and I love that.
I also love the idiotically long bonnet,
and the 571 horsepowers
that live beneath it.
I love the speed of the roof, too.
You really can get it up or down at...
a set of lights. I love its doors.
I love its windscreen wipers.
I love the dust caps on the tyre valves.
I love the men who made
it, I love Germany.
I want to move there, and
have cold meat for breakfast,
and wear shorts.
I also love the way that in here,
it just feels like a Mercedes,
apart from that, obviously.
And that, and that, and that.
I mean, apart from the launch control
and all those buttons
there it feels normal.
There's no sense that you're in a
swivel-eyed destroyer of worlds.
There are many cars on the market today
for people who want to be sensible.
The SLS is rare because
it's for people who don't.
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
I like it, that's just...
You love this thing, don't you?
It's such a perfect car. It is perfect.
I can see why you love it,
looking at you with it.
Think about it.
It's loud, old-fashioned, not sensible,
it's got a hole in the top,
it's you, with a tax disc.
That's what it is. Yes, it is.
And now, we must find out how
fast it goes round our track,
and that means handing it over
to our tame racing driver.
Some say that he's the
only man in Britain
who knows what B&Q stands for.
And that he can't give his
million-pound bonus back
because he's already spent it...
on French breast implants.
All we know is... he's called The Stig.
And he's off. Nice, clean
start on this crisp, dry day.
That is pure engine sound
you're hearing, by the way.
No active exhaust valve
nonsense in the SLS.
First corner.
He's getting a bit sideways on
the way out, but he's through!
MUSIC: Theme tune from "The Archers"
Sorry, I should explain,
the Stig has become a massive
Archers fan recently.
He keeps it tidy through
Chicago down to Hammerhead.
This is a car that needs
very precise driving.
Too violent with the
steering, throttle or brakes
and it will bite you.
Look at that. Beautifully done.
VOICES FROM THE ARCHERS:
'I'll be as quick as I can.
'I can help, if that'll
speed things up.'
Rural drivel there.
Up the gears to Follow-Through
like all flappy-pedal boxers.
Not so good in town, but
it works brilliantly here.
OK, he's passed the tyres.
Roadster is 40 kilos heavier than
the Coupe, so will it be slower?
We'll never know, because the
Coupe has never been round here.
That's Gambon done and across the line!
It did it...
No. Higher than that.
1.19.6, so it's there,
between the Lamborghini Gallardo
and a Ferrari Scuderia.
Not bad, but it's hardly
in the medals, is it?
What this is, it's like
Robert Downey Jnr.
He's never won an Oscar,
but he's still brilliant.
Anyway...
I've got no idea what that means.
Yes, well, you work it out,
because it is time to put a star
in our reasonably-priced car.
Is it Robert Downey Junior? No.
But he is an American, like you.
I'm not.
Ladies and gentlemen, please
welcome Matt Le Blanc!
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
Have a seat. He's here!
That's a good welcome.
Now, first of all,
hearty congratulations
on your Golden Globe.
Last week, wasn't it?
Last week or the week before,
I don't know, I had to fly...
I came back here after Christmas...
Is it easier to win an award or lose one
in terms of getting your face right?
I'm never quite sure.
If you win, you've got to
look proud, but not smug,
and that's a tricky thing to do.
I've got a lot of practice
at the losing face.
The losing face? Yes.
The camera sits at your
table and stays on you
and the guy's halfway through his speech
and they still have a
camera on you... so you...
LAUGHTER
He deserved it, yeah.
We lost spectacularly last week to
a programme called This Morning.
You know this? No. It's a programme...
Fix! Fix!
Well, no, it's a programme where men
put their fingers in other men.
LAUGHTER
They did! And as a result of that,
we were blown out of the water.
The viewing public likes that more.
So well done, This Morning.
You won your Golden Globe for Episodes.
I don't know if anybody
here has seen Episodes.
I think it is just brilliant.
Thank you.
You've just done the second series,
which is why you're here.
We finished a few days ago.
Talk us through the plot.
Because of those of you
who have not seen yet
OK, it's a show about a fictitious
show that starts in the UK
and it's bought by the American networks
to be revamped and remade in the States.
They promise them the
world and one by one,
every promise is broken, including
the fact that they keep
their lead actor played by Richard
Griffiths and they tell him,
"No, can't have him.
You're going to hire a Matt Le Blanc."
So I play this weird,
bizarre version of myself.
Of course, Episodes has not
yet become the huge hit.
What you're best known for is...
Well, I tell you what,
let's show you a clip of you
in your best role. Here it is.
This is Bob Seger, obviously.
Night Moves.
This was the video shot in 1994,
and if we look very carefully,
here's the heroine and... whoa!
Wait a minute! Who is that?!
That was '94.
Friends had already started in '94,
so you were moonlighting
in Seger videos.
A friend of mine directed
that and he called me
and said, "Hey, I'm doing a video
for Bob Seger for Night Moves.
"Do you want to be the hero guy?
" And I said, "Sure, yeah."
So I go down there and they get in
the little trailer to get ready,
we're at this drive-in theatre,
and someone knocks on the door
and says, "Bob Seger would like
to see you in his motor home."
So I go over and I go into the motor
home and he starts talking me through
what it was like when he was
young and going to the drive-in
and trying to pick up girls and he
breaks out a bottle of tequila.
Next thing I know, we down
a whole bottle of tequila,
Bob Seger and I, and then
they knock on the door,
"Ready for you on set!
" So I'm drunk in the whole video.
And it wasn't just that.
You were also in a Tom Petty video.
Drunk in that one too.
Drunk today? Hmm, yeah. A little bit.
Now, cars. I know you are
what we call a petrol head,
I think you call a gear head.
We know this...
I've got an inkling of it,
because when I was watching Episodes,
we've got a clip here which
gives us a bit of an insight.
Let's just run this.
Tell me that's not yours! You like?
Oh!
I read there was only three
in the whole world. Yes.
Me, the Sultan of Brunei
and some drug guy.
Oh, it's magnificent.
Here.
And that's while I was never picked.
Really? Go for it!
I am SO happy.
Oh!
Get a room! Can I?
I wish I knew how to drive.
That's an Alfa 8C convertible.
That's a very rare car.
You end up in an XK
in that first series.
Right. That was a funny story
about that car because
when they agree to let us use it in
the show, it hadn't been sold yet.
By the time we needed it,
someone had bought it,
so it showed up with its own
security team and everything else.
I got to drive it maybe five feet.
YOU did? Yeah.
Steve drove it further than I did.
This year, it's Ron Dennis's
personal Mercedes SLR he loaned us.
What was that like?
I didn't get to drive that one either!
You're the only one crazy enough to let
me behind the wheel, apparently.
Now, your car history is chequered,
Isn't it? At best, yes.
You had an Audi 5000,
which we'd call 100.
That was the one that had the
unintended acceleration stories.
Yeah, not the one I had,
but I heard about that.
It was like a crap shoot.
And then there was a
Fiat X1/9 that came,
which is like a motorised vajazzle,
I always think, the X1/9.
Yeah, that was probably a mistake.
I bought it at a used car lot.
I was driving by and, you know, "Ooh!
"That looks like a good waste
of money right there."
You used to have a Porsche
Turbo, didn't you?
Yeah, I had a 2000 996 turbo.
As I understand it, you modified that,
cos when we buy cars in
Europe, BMWs or Porsches
or whatever they might be,
that's what they're like,
whereas in the States,
there seems to be a culture of you
buy a car and then you take it
to a shop and somebody tweaks
it and fiddles with it.
Right. Is that something you
just feel you have to do?
Well, for me, it's like, if someone who
doesn't know anything about cars
can just go down to the
store and get the same car,
that's not right.
I mean, I love cars, so I should
go a LITTLE faster, I think.
So what did you do to the Turbo?
The Turbo, I had a Gemballa
computer programme put in it
and an exhaust and TechArt suspension.
Then I took it in to have the mass
air sensor was starting to...
This is probably super-boring
for most people.
No, it's Top Gear, for once you're
allowed to talk about this.
The Tonight Show wouldn't let
me talk about any of this.
Are you a man who goes
and drives on circuits?
Occasionally, yeah,
mostly with the bikes.
I know that's a sore subject with you.
No, you can talk about bikes.
You've got three seconds.
And they're up.
So, have you ever driven
round Laguna Seca,
which is your nearest track, I guess?
Yeah, Willow Springs is probably closer,
but Laguna Seca is such a
beautiful facility.
You know, the Corkscrew there.
The Corkscrew is a corner
that I just find impossible
to get round without crashing.
Six stories I think it drops.
It's left, right, it's six stories.
Yeah, it's not my idea of fun.
Our track is much easier.
I know you took your trip
down here quite seriously,
because you told our researcher,
you were asking about the Kia
and the roll cage, which you said,
"Ah, that'll make it more rigid."
We've never had any of this before
from a guest, somebody that keen on it.
That's probably the best
handling Kia there is.
Pretty nice little car.
Who here would like to see Matt's lap?
AUDIENCE CHEERS IN ASSENT
Me too, yeah!
Let's have a look.
Just don't use the brake
as much, that's all.
No, you're going to
need the brakes there.
Were you OK with having a
stick-shift on your left?
Yeah, I missed a couple of
shifts here and there, but...
Well, that looks, that's the sort
of tidy corner. Sloppy at best.
We're keeping it the tidy through there.
The more boring it looks,
the faster it often is.
That's, well, very boring indeed
through there. Hammerhead.
Almost got the front wheel off
the ground there, but not quite.
That's very tight on the way out.
Matt whisting
It was obviously boring you
to death as well out there.
Flat through there, yeah, no lifting.
Your heart is beating
once every three hours.
You're going to cut this one.
Yeah... that's very cut. Gambon, cut it.
Oh, yes, very cut.
And there we are, across the line.
What do you reckon? Um...
Well, hopefully in the
top half somewhere.
Hopefully in the top half.
Well, often when laps look
that drama-less, as it were,
they can be quite fast.
So there's the board.
Rowan Atkinson currently leading 1.42.2.
That's quick.
Yes, 1.42.2 is unbelievably quick.
Halfway would put you
with Bob Geldof, 1.48.1.
You did it, Matt Le
Blanc, in one minute...
40...
two...
AUDIENCE GASPS
one.
RAPTUROUS CHEERING
Fastest ever!
Fastest ever! That's not bad.
I just knew when I started...
Are you serious? Absolutely serious.
You were apparently running at
1.42.2, absolutely level with Rowan,
who, by the way, has just hung himself,
and then on the last lap,
popped in at 1.42.1. Wow!
So there we are, ladies and gentlemen,
the fastest guest we've ever had.
Matt Le Blanc!
Thank you so much.
Thank you, thanks.
Now, we may be in a spot of
economic bother at the moment,
however, Rolls-Royce, Bentley and
Aston Martin are all enjoying
record sales, and all because
of demand from China.
The thing is, though, that people with
adenoids are saying in five years' time,
the Chinese are going
to stop buying our cars
and WE will start buying theirs.
In fact, if I had a pound
for everyone who said,
"Soon you will be driving a Chinese car
," I'd be able to afford a Chinese car.
To see if they have a point, Jeremy
and I decided to pop over to
Beijing and find out what
all the fuss is about.
[Back ground music : Brian Eno - Passing Over starts playing]
For the last 50 years,
there have been two types
of transport in China.
If you were Chairman Mao, you had
a honky, red-flag armoured limo.
If you were not Chairman
Mao, you had one of these.
Or if you were really lucky,
you had one of these.
Even in the early '90s,
the idea that you would
own a car was complete madness,
because you'd never have
been able to afford it,
and even if you could afford it,
you weren't allowed to have one.
Now, though, things have changed.
In 1977, there were one
million cars in China.
By 2008, there were 51 million.
Now there are 85 million.
And every day that
number swells by 38,000.
Somebody buys a new car in
China every 2.3 seconds.
To keep up with demand,
China's car factories are
running at light speed.
Last year, the whole of Europe combined
produced 16.9 million vehicles.
China all on its own produced
1.3 million more than that.
And it's not just Chinese companies-
that are cashing in on the boom.
Audi is now making long-wheelbase
versions of its cars
specifically for sale in
China and nowhere else,
because in China, space in the back-
matters more than anything else.
China is now the world's
second-biggest oil consumer,
taking more barrels per day
than India and Japan combined.
By 2025, the road network
will be big enough to cover
the whole of the British Isles...
all of it, Scottish
Highlands, the lot...
20 times over.
So where did it all begin?
Well, one of the first cars ever
to be sold in China was this.
The CA6410UA.
Better known to you and I
as the Austin Maestro.
Actually, it's the
back end of a Maestro,
but the front end of a Montego, and
it's powered by a Toyota engine.
The history behind this car
though is even more complicated.
In 1998, a Chinese tobacco
company bought the tooling
for the Maestro and the Montego
so they could be made in China.
In order to make them in China,
they had to tell the authorities
that they were building buses.
This car... or I should say THESE cars,
because this is a bit
of a cut-and-shut job...
these were terrible when they
were being built in Britain,
so imagine what they like when they
were being made using worn-out tools
by a company that's the Chinese
equivalent of Player's No 6.
It's just hopeless!
Pretty soon, various bright
sparks in China started to think.
Why buy the rights to
make cars we don't want
when we can just copy
the ones we DO want?
The Chinese are very good
at this sort of thing.
I'm speaking to you from
behind a pair of fake Ray-Bans
wearing a fake Armani jacket,
carrying a fate Louis Vuitton bag,
in which we find a fake iPad
and a fake iPhone.
And if we consult my fake Omega,
we see that it's 2.35. probably.
Which means it is time to pop into
the fake Starbucks over there
for a cup of fake coffee.
It seems, then, that the expression...
"copyright infringement"
doesn't translate terribly
well into Mandarin.
All of which explains this.
It looks like a BMW X5,
but actually, it's a blatant copy called
the Shuanhuan S-CEO HBJ6474Y.
Then there's this, a
copy of the Fiat Panda.
And this, a copy of the Smart ForTwo.
And this, a copy of the Daewoo Matiz.
Did you hear about the
Lifan motorcycles?
Lifan is a Chinese company that make
copies of small Honda motorcycles,
but to make sure you don't notice,
they change the name on the tank.
To what? Hongda. H-O-N-G-D-A.
Hongda? So on that basis,
is this Mini a Minging?
It should be, yes.
Because it is the most
tragic-looking thing. It's awful.
It's like somebody's
described Mini to somebody
on the telephone.
Or sent a blurry fax.
"There we are, that's
what it looks like."
It is very cheap. How much is it?
£4,100. That is cheap.
But this Toyota Aygo over
here is only£3,500.
It's not a Aygo. That's an FO.
That's what it's called. FO.
I think that's a message to Toyota
if Toyota ever decide
to sue the fake makers.
Do these people ever get taken to court?
Yeah. BMW sued the people making
the X5 fake and they lost.
Really? Yeah.
The Chinese government said,
"No, it doesn't look like
anything like an X5."
That's funny, I thought they looked...
really similar. No, they don't.
Don't they? No. It's just me?
No, it's just you. Right. OK.
It's easy to see why they were copying
because when they tried to go it alone,
the results weren't very good.
This tripod is the XF15OZK-4,
and naturally, we
couldn't wait to try it.
Right.
You see one yet...
Oh, God!
James!
'On the plus side, we now
knew where the engine was,
'information that came in handy
about 20 seconds later.'
ENGINE STRUGGLES TO START
Come on!
'After some local bodging, we
were back in and on our way.'
Wow!
Oh, that's reverse.
That's gone into nought, fifth, second.
First, that was it.
Fourth.
That's going to look very
funny from the outside, that.
Now you're doing second.
'Having mastered the gearbox,
it was time to open up
'the single-cylinder
12-horsepower engine.'
The acceleration is blinding!
It's like a safety device.
You accelerate too hard, your
feet come off the pedal.
Hold on to your spine. Ah!
2004, this car was launched.
If I'd shown this to
you and asked you when
it was built, when
would you have said?
1957. I would say it was
older than me. Yeah.
Ow! Ow!
Poor quality!
BOTH: Uh!
Come on, redeeming feature, James.
There must be a redeeming feature.
Er... It's character-building.
No, because I mean this... BOTH: Oh, no!
CARS HORNS BEEP
ENGINE STRUGGLES TO START
I think our test drive's over.
So we moved on to look at some
more modern Chinese cars.
This is the JACJ7.
At the 6th annual Chinese
government procurement conference,
it won the highly coveted
first choice in middle class
of government procurement award.
And then there's the
Haval M2 which is...
Well, we have absolutely
no idea what it is.
Can I read you something
from the blurb? Yeah.
About the styling of the M2.
I think this absolutely sums it up.
"Body on the side of the
lion to go straight fair
"with enough of the masculine
qualities of men."
If we're honest, the M2 and
the J7 aren't much good.
So, are there any
Chinese cars which are?
Well, this is a Guangzhou Trumpchi.
And it's not made from tin
foil or bits of old Austin.
Underneath, it's an Alfa Romeo 166.
This might be all right.
I think, however, that this
Roewe 350 will be even better.
The Roewe 350 is particularly important,
because it will eventually become
an MG in Britain, the MG 5.
It will be changed slightly.
The engine will be different because
it needs to meet legislation
for emissions, and so on.
But basically, I'm driving
a car that you will
be able to buy in Britain very soon.
Essentially, then, what we have
here is an Alfa Romeo and an MG.
Those, of course, are
very sporting names,
and that's why we've come to
this very picturesque racetrack.
What we're going to do is see
which of these cars can set
the fastest lap time.
Well, WE'RE not. No, we're not.
We're going to use our
tame racing driver.
Some say he's the Stig, but he isn't.
He is the Stig's Chinese cousin.
Now, I should explain, driving
is his second favourite thing.
What's his first favourite thing?
Attacking people. He does it a lot.
He's constantly at it.
Why are you doing that?
Why don't you go and do some driving?
Do some driving. Get into the car!
Stop attacking us! Get in the car.
No, he's got to get in the car.
Get in the car.
Trumpchi. Trumpchi.
Get in the Trumpchi. No!
No, that's the director.
That's the director!
What if I start the
engine, would that do it?
Come on, come on, in you go.
They bow, don't they?
Go in. Get in. Oh, yes!
That's the worst Stig we've ever had.
HE COUNTS DOWN
Attack Stig doesn't attack
the throttle, does he?
Good-looking car, that.
It is a good-looking car,
it's growing on me.
It's got the boot shape of
the Lancia Gamma. Yeah.
And it has an Alfa engine. Does it? Yes.
But it is called a Trumpchi.
It is, but...
That is quite funny.
What are you driving these days, Jeremy?
Well, it's interesting...
underneath, it's an Alfa.
It is a Trumpchi.
Attack Stig is back, everybody!
Watch out! And across the line.
1.50, dead.
We've got to get him out of
that car and into the Roewe.
Get him in the Roewe as
quickly as possible.
Get him in the Roewe! It's interesting.
He's attacking the starter.
I thought it was a racist thing,
he just didn't like us.
He's coming towards us now. No.
You were good! 150 dead.
Eventually, Attack Stig was
corralled into James's Roewe.
HE COUNTS DOWN
That begins quickly.
How many horsepower has it got? 107.
That's a 1.5, isn't it?
How have they got so few horsepower?
I don't know.
And I don't like to sound like you,
But that's not enough power.
Because they called it
Roewe, because Roewe...
BOTH: Is how they would say Rover.
Yeah. I thought they'd say Lover.
The seconds ticked by, but
there was no sign of my Roewe.
Where has he gone? I don't know.
After we dragged Attack
Stig off the marshal...
Across the line!
We got a clean lap time for the Roewe.
Victory by one tenth of a second.
A fairly hollow victory, though, as...
we estimate that on the same track
a comparable European car would
be ten or 15 seconds faster.
So, what about safety?
Chinese crash tests are much the
same as the ones we have in Europe.
But the speeds are a bit lower.
Any injuries? None at all. Nothing?
Not a scratch. What about the car?
No damage at all. Really?
No. That's a pass.
Are you ready?
ELECTRONIC CHINESE VOICE
Having satisfied ourselves
that these cars
had been through all their crash tests,
we were confident that we could take
them onto the streets of Beijing.
This might not be as nice to drive,
or as fast or as safe as a European car,
but it offers everything the
Chinese motorist would want.
There's lots of space in the
back, a couple of nice gadgets,
wooden trim and enough headroom
for anyone up to five foot three.
The editor of a Chinese car
magazine told me this morning
that the Chinese like good
equipment in cars, good gadgets.
And this actually does quite well.
It has got sat-nav, incomprehensible
of course, reversing cameras,
decent audio system,
automatic air-conditioning,
audio controls on the steering wheel,
digital dashboard... pretty good.
I'd like to say that this
feels like an old Alfa Romeo,
but it doesn't really, chiefly
because of the automatic gearbox,
which was made by a man who
I think is a greengrocer.
Certainly, he has no comprehension
of what an automatic gearbox should do.
Stop changing gear! Don't do that!
It's all very well Jeremy whining
and shouting at his gearbox,
but he should try this.
This is a three-speed
automatic with overdrive.
It's quite smooth, actually,
but as a concept,
it's just a tad old-fashioned.
It is worth bearing in mind,
though, that both these cars
cost £12,000, and that in China,
a base model Audi A3 is
more than twice that.
If you bear that price
difference in mind
and ignore the gearbox,
it's really not too bad.
Rides nicely.
CLUNK!
Most of the time. Er...
At this point, we ran out of
things... to say about our cars,
so we met up for a discussion.
So, James May, would you buy
a Roewe 350 in Britain? No.
No. No. Would you buy a Trumpchi?
Only if it was very cheap.
But look at it this way.
In just five years, China
has gone from making that,
whatever it is, to making these.
With that rate of progress,
where are they going to
be in five years' time?
That does take us back to
our original question...
in five years' time,
everybody will be driving
Chinese cars... yes,
we probably will.
We are doomed. We are doomed.
We've absolutely...
In the plums.
THEME TUNE PLAYED IN THE STYLE OF
TRADITIONAL CHINESE MUSIC
Sync and corrections by APOLLO
www.addic7ed.com